<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../meta/asischema.xsd"
   xml:base="schnitzler-interviews" xml:id="I011" next="I085" prev="I032">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">Arthur Schnitzler: »Das Zeitlose ist von kürzester Dauer.« Interviews,
               Meinungen, Proteste (1891–1931)</title>
            <title level="a" ref="#pmb32917">David Ewen: Schnitzler, Old, Admires America’s Young
               Vigor, 11. 1. 1931</title>
            <title type="iso-date" when-iso="1931-01-11" n="1">11. 1. 1931</title>
            <author ref="#pmb11277">Ewen, David</author>
            <editor>
               <name>Müller, Martin Anton</name>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>ASI</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transkription und Kommentierung</resp>
               <name>Martin Anton Müller</name>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Martin Anton Müller</publisher>
            <idno type="asi" n="011"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listBibl>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#pmb11277">Ewen, David</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#pmb32917">Schnitzler, Old, Admires America’s Young
                        Vigor. Is sorry He Put Off Coming Until Too Late</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j" ref="#pmb58357">The World</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1931-01-11" n="1">11. 1. 1931</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="jg">71</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">25.345</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">7</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en-US">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="approved">
         <change who="MAM" when="2017-11-17">angelegt</change>
         <change who="MAM" when="2021-09-15">Index check</change>
         <change who="KH" when="2021-10-29">Durchsicht</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader><text type="text">
      <body>
         <div type="image">
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Strichzeichung – Schnitzlers Porträt im Halbprofil. Unterschrift Leo Kober</figDesc>
               <graphic url="./images/1931-ewen-vigor.png" width="3.5cm"/>
            </figure>
            <caption>
               <rs type="person" ref="#pmb2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs>
            </caption>
         </div>
         <div type="original" xml:lang="en-US">
            <head>
               <rs type="person" ref="#pmb2121">Schnitzler</rs>, Old, Admires <rs type="place"
                  ref="#pmb175">America</rs>’s Young Vigor.</head>
            <head type="sub">Is sorry He Put Off Coming Until Too Late</head>
            <head type="sub">By David Ewen</head>
            <p>Now that <rs type="person" ref="#pmb2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs>, the famous German
               novelist and playwright, is growing old his deepest regret is that he has never
               visited <rs type="place" ref="#pmb175">America</rs>. It is true that men far older
               than he have successfully made the trip across the ocean. Only recently, Sir <rs
                  type="person" ref="#pmb5194">George Henschel</rs>, the <rs type="place"
                  ref="#pmb254">English</rs> composer and conductor came here to help the <rs
                  type="org" ref="#pmb29427">Boston Symphony Orchestra</rs> celebrate its fiftieth
               anniversary – and Sir <rs type="person" ref="#pmb5194">George</rs> has already seen
               his eightieth year. A man, however, is as old as he feels – and, though <rs
                  type="person" ref="#pmb2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs> is only sixty-eight, he feels
               <anchor type="textConst" xml:id="T_I011-12"/>much, much<note type='textConst' xml:id="T_I011-12h"><quote>much, much,</quote></note> older. His face is deeply wrinkled. His eyes are dull and appear sad and
               tired over heavy bags, he walks with a heavy gait and with stooped back. In spirit
               and in flesh he is already an old man.</p>
            <p>But though he is old and feels that death cannot be very far away, there is by no
               means any melancholy or despair in him.</p>
            <p>
               <ref target="#q168" type="question"/>
               <anchor type="label" xml:id="I011_L2_todie"/>»Younger men than I have been known to
               die,« he said softly and peacefully – one could easily see that the contemplation of
               death did not frighten him in the least. »I have worked hard during my life, and when
               the time comes I am quite prepared to go. Of course, as long as life is spared me so
               long will there be more and more work for me to complete. My pen is never idle. I am
               now working on three books, and should it be fated that I complete them all I shall
               gladly begin work on others. However, I am always ready to drop my pen, because I
               feel and know that I have lived both wisely and well during my lifetime. At least my
               conscience in that direction is clear.«</p>
            <head type="sub">
               <rs type="place" ref="#pmb175">America</rs> Today Is <rs type="place" ref="#pmb468"
                  >Europe</rs> Tomorrow</head>
            <p>
               <ref target="#q130" type="question"/>And a moment, later he added, as though in
               afterthought: »But I do have one deep regret. My greatest sorrow at present is that I
               have never visited your remarkable <rs type="place" ref="#pmb175">country</rs>, and
               therefore have never had the enviable opportunity of seeing it and studying it at
               first hand. And, unfortunately, I am now too old to remedy this!«</p>
            <p>
               <anchor type="label" xml:id="I011_L1_bookcase"/>We were sitting on the comfortably
               soft couch in <rs type="person" ref="#pmb2121">Arthur <latex alt="Schnitz\-ler">Schnitzler</latex>’s</rs> charming
               study. The walls are <anchor type="textConst" xml:id="T_I011-1"/>covered<note
                  type="textConst" xml:id="T_I011-1h">
                  <quote>cov</quote>
               </note> with bookcases heavily lined with books. One of these bookcases, modestly
               covered by a velvet curtain, contains all of <rs type="person" ref="#pmb2121">Arthur
                  Schnitzler</rs>’s works in all translated languages. The one window of the room
               looks out upon a luxuriously fertile <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I011-1"
               />garden, where during the spring, summer and early autumn Dr. <rs type="person"
                  ref="#pmb2121">Schnitzler</rs> does all of his writing<note type="commentary"
                  xml:id="K_I011-1h">Das dürfte er nicht gesagt haben; die Aussage, dass er nicht im
                  Freien arbeite, ist wahrscheinlich richtig: <ref target="#I072_L1_gartenarbeit"
                     type="pointer"/>.
               </note>. It was rapidly becoming dusk, and the room – as we were talking – was
               becoming suffused with a serene, mellow darkness. <rs type="person" ref="#pmb2121"
                  >Schnitzler</rs> did not trouble putting on the light. He was buried in the
               softness of the couch and he was quietly speaking to me about <rs type="place"
                  ref="#pmb175">America</rs>.</p>
            <p>
               <ref target="#q169" type="question"/>»I have no illusions about <rs type="place"
                  ref="#pmb175">America</rs> being something of a Utopia in the miniature,« he said,
               »for I well know that it is nothing of the sort. But <rs type="place" ref="#pmb175"
                  >America</rs> interests me profoundly – and has interested me for many years
               already – because it obviously points the way to the future. Whether we are at
               harmony with this future or not; whether, even, this future is a desirable one, is
               beside the point – nor is it a question I would care particularly to discuss now. The
               fact remains that this future is almost inevitable, and whether we like it or not we
               must accept it. Tomorrow <rs type="place" ref="#pmb468">Europe</rs> will be what <rs
                  type="place" ref="#pmb175">America</rs> is today – and if we are interested in
               ourselves we must inevitably be interested in <rs type="place" ref="#pmb175"
                  >America</rs> too. You have led the way in industry, politics and finance. I
               frankly feel that it will not be very long before you will likewise lead the way in
               matters artistic too.</p>
            <latex alt="\newpage"/>
            <head type="sub">Says <rs type="place" ref="#pmb468">Europe</rs> Lacks Our Vigor In
               Literature</head>
            <p>
               <ref target="#q169" type="question"/>»From what I have heard and from what I have
               read I have gathered the fact that <rs type="place" ref="#pmb175">America</rs> is
               creating a new, unique form of art and culture – a type uniquely its own and one
               which strongly points toward being the art and culture of the future. That is why I
               was so eager to visit <rs type="place" ref="#pmb175">America</rs>, to try to feel its
               atmosphere and spirit and to try, perhaps, to understand it. Unfortunately, I
               procrastinated too long.«</p>
            <p>Dr. Schnitzler was speaking about our unique art. Was he, perhaps, acquainted with
               our literature?</p>
            <p>
               <ref target="#q170" type="question"/>»Quite naturally, many of your writers have time
               and again come to my notice – and from time to time I have come across much that
               impressed me very, very deeply. Names at the moment elude me. But I can say, at the
               very least, that you have two outstanding great novelists, and certainly at least one
               profound dramatist. Both <rs type="person" ref="#pmb6859">Theodore Dreiser</rs> and
                  <rs type="person" ref="#pmb60597">Sinclair Lewis</rs> (Note: At the time of the
               conversation it was not yet known that <rs type="person" ref="#pmb60597">Sinclair
                  Lewis</rs> was the <rs type="org" ref="#pmb29679">Nobel prize</rs> winner) have
               contributed something new and original to the novel. We <rs type="place"
                  ref="#pmb468">Europeans</rs> find a vigor and vitality in both <rs type="person"
                  ref="#pmb6859">Dreiser</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="#pmb60597">Lewis</rs> which
               is simply lacking over here. Such prose – palpitant and alive – could have come only
               from an <rs type="place" ref="#pmb175">American</rs>. And such messages, as their
               novels express, are intrinsically <rs type="place" ref="#pmb175">American</rs>. As
               for <rs type="person" ref="#pmb5198">Eugene O’Neill</rs>, he is to me one of the
               greatest figures in contemporary drama. I personally, found his ›<rs type="work"
                  ref="#pmb33191">Strange Interlude</rs>‹ to be prolix and outmoded; this business
               of the ›aside‹ is neither original nor of artistic importance, it seems to me. It is
               such a naive trick to tell what is in a character’s mind which a little bit of
               subtlety would have accomplished with far more aptness. But in his earlier plays – in
                  ›<rs type="work" ref="#pmb60603">All God's Chillun Got Wings</rs>‹, and in his
                  ›<rs type="work" ref="#pmb60605">Emperor Jones</rs>‹ – he is a truly great figure.
               These plays grew out of <rs type="place" ref="#pmb175">American</rs> soil. Their
               supreme strength lies not only in the fact that, taken from artistic standards, they
               are great plays, but also in the fact that these plays could not possibly have come
               from a <rs type="place" ref="#pmb468">European</rs> pen. In the drama, as well as in
               the novel, <rs type="place" ref="#pmb175">America</rs> is now fully emancipated.</p>
            <p>
               <ref target="#q169" type="question"/>»But what impresses me most about <rs
                  type="place" ref="#pmb175">America</rs> is its remarkably experimental nature, it
               is constantly alert to new ideas and thoughts, far more alert than <rs type="place"
                  ref="#pmb468">Europe</rs> can hope to be. Take such inventions as the motion
               picture – and now the talking picture and the radio and, you will find that in <rs
                  type="place" ref="#pmb175">America</rs> these have become in a bewilderingly short
               time, an integral part of <rs type="place" ref="#pmb175">American</rs> life. Such
               open-mindedness to new things has, undoubtedly, given <rs type="place" ref="#pmb175"
                  >America</rs> the reputation of constantly pursuing new fads. But this, far from
               being a regrettable state of affairs, is to me most commendable. It is a healthy
               condition in which it is comparatively easy to make gigantic strides forward in the
               future in scientific and artistic matters. It is the proper soil in which fruit can
               blossom with most fertility.</p>
            <p>
               <ref target="#q171" type="question"/>»You say in <rs type="place" ref="#pmb175"
                  >America</rs> that the drama is dying? To me, of course, such a fear is
               ridiculous. An art can never die. True, drama, because of certain inevitable
               conditions, is in a sort of stagnancy: fluctuating periods of stagnation and
               fertility are inevitable in the life of every art. But to say it is dead, especially
               when you <rs type="place" ref="#pmb175">Americans</rs> have a man like <rs
                  type="person" ref="#pmb5198">Eugene O’Neill</rs> in your midst, is futile
               pessimism.</p>
            <p>
               <ref target="#q172" type="question"/>»Talking pictures can never replace the spoken
               drama. I do not deny the importance of the talking picture as a new type of artistic
               expression – but it is a type of artistic expression different from the spoken drama.
               Talking pictures may supplement the drama, but they will never supplant it. At its
               best it will be eighth lively art – and an art in which, I am confident, <rs
                  type="place" ref="#pmb175">America</rs> will prove to be supreme.«</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biographical">
            <div1>
               <ref type="schnitzler-tagebuch" target="1930-08-15"/>
               <quote>Nm. <rs type="person" ref="#pmb11277">David Ewes</rs>, junger Journalist <rs
                     type="place" ref="#pmb44053">New York</rs>, dem ich ein Interview abgeschlagen;
                  Gespräch.–</quote>
            </div1>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listPerson>
            <person xml:id="pmb11277">
               <persName>
                  <forename>David</forename>
                  <surname>Ewen</surname>
               </persName>
               <birth>
                  <date when="1907-11-26">26.11.1907</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb46224">
                     <placeName type="pref">Lviv</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>49,83826 24,02324</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </birth>
               <death>
                  <date when="1985-12-28">28.12.1985</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb45749">
                     <placeName type="pref">Miami</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>25,77427 -80,19366</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </death>
               <sex value="male"/>
               <occupation ref="pmb99">Journalist/Journalistin</occupation>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                  >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/person_14828</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="d-nb">https://d-nb.info/gnd/1089844891</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/11277/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q9202613</idno>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pmb2121">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Arthur</forename>
                  <surname>Schnitzler</surname>
               </persName>
               <birth>
                  <date when="1862-05-15">15.05.1862</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb50">
                     <placeName type="pref">Wien</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>48,2066 16,37341</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </birth>
               <death>
                  <date when="1931-10-21">21.10.1931</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb50">
                     <placeName type="pref">Wien</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>48,2066 16,37341</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </death>
               <sex value="male"/>
               <occupation ref="pmb90">Schriftsteller/Schriftstellerin</occupation>
               <occupation ref="pmb97">Mediziner/Medizinerin</occupation>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="d-nb">https://d-nb.info/gnd/118609807</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-bahr"
                  >https://schnitzler-bahr.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb2121.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/2121/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-briefe"
                  >https://schnitzler-briefe.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pages/hits.html?searchkey=pmb2121</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                  >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/pmb2121</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="fackel">https://fackel.oeaw.ac.at/?p=fackelp38500</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="kraus1933"
                  >https://kraus1933.ace.oeaw.ac.at/Gesamt.xml?template=register_personen.html&amp;letter=S#DWpers0212</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="doi">https://doi.org/10.1553/0x00284416</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q44331</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikipedia"
                  >https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Schnitzler</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-kino"
                  >https://schnitzler-kino.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb2121.html</idno>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pmb5194">
               <persName>
                  <forename>George</forename>
                  <surname>Henschel</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="person_geburtsname-vorname">Georg</persName>
               <birth>
                  <date when="1850-02-18">18.02.1850</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb677">
                     <placeName type="pref">Breslau</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>51,10773 17,03533</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </birth>
               <death>
                  <date when="1934-09-10">10.09.1934</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb55351">
                     <placeName type="pref">Aviemore</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>57,19553 -3,8259</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </death>
               <sex value="male"/>
               <occupation ref="pmb107">Sänger/Sängerin</occupation>
               <occupation ref="pmb131">Dirigent/Dirigentin</occupation>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="d-nb">https://d-nb.info/gnd/116719710</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/5194/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q64238</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikipedia"
                  >https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Henschel</idno>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pmb6859">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Theodore</forename>
                  <surname>Dreiser</surname>
               </persName>
               <birth>
                  <date when="1871-08-27">27.08.1871</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb48329">
                     <placeName type="pref">Terre Haute</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>39,4667 -87,41391</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </birth>
               <death>
                  <date when="1945-12-28">28.12.1945</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb38174">
                     <placeName type="pref">Hollywood</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>26,0112 -80,14949</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </death>
               <sex value="male"/>
               <occupation ref="pmb90">Schriftsteller/Schriftstellerin</occupation>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                  >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/person_14510</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="d-nb">https://d-nb.info/gnd/118527355</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/6859/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="fackel">https://fackel.oeaw.ac.at/?p=fackelp54060</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q486096</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikipedia"
                  >https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodore_Dreiser</idno>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pmb60597">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Sinclair</forename>
                  <surname>Lewis</surname>
               </persName>
               <birth>
                  <date when="1885-05-07">1885-05-07</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb60599">
                     <placeName type="pref">Sauk Centre</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>45,73747 -94,95252</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </birth>
               <death>
                  <date when="1951-01-10">1951-01-10</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb445">
                     <placeName type="pref">Rom</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>41,89193 12,51133</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </death>
               <sex value="male"/>
               <occupation ref="pmb90">Schriftsteller/Schriftstellerin</occupation>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/60597/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="d-nb">https://d-nb.info/gnd/118572490</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="fackel">https://fackel.oeaw.ac.at/?p=fackelp53340</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q123469</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikipedia"
                  >https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sinclair_Lewis</idno>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pmb5198">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Eugene</forename>
                  <surname>O’Neill</surname>
               </persName>
               <birth>
                  <date when="1888-10-16">16.10.1888</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb44053">
                     <placeName type="pref">New York City</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>40,71427 -74,00597</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </birth>
               <death>
                  <date when="1953-11-27">27.11.1953</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb889">
                     <placeName type="pref">Boston (Massachusetts)</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>42,35843 -71,05977</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </death>
               <sex value="male"/>
               <occupation ref="pmb90">Schriftsteller/Schriftstellerin</occupation>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="d-nb">https://d-nb.info/gnd/118590014</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                  >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/person_18555</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/5198/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="fackel">https://fackel.oeaw.ac.at/?p=fackelp50755</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q93157</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikipedia"
                  >https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eugene_O%E2%80%99Neill</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-kino"
                  >https://schnitzler-kino.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb5198.html</idno>
            </person>
         </listPerson>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pmb33191">
               <title>Seltsames Zwischenspiel</title>
               <title type="namensvariante">Strange Interlude</title>
               <author ref="pmb5198" role="hat-geschaffen">O’Neill, Eugene</author>
               <date notBefore="1928-01-01" when="1928-07-01">1928</date>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/33191/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                  >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb33191.html</idno>
               <note type="work_kind">Drama &gt;&gt; Mehraktiges Drama</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pmb60603">
               <title>All God’s Chillun Got Wings</title>
               <title type="namensvariante">Alle Kinder Gottes haben Flügel</title>
               <author ref="pmb5198" role="hat-geschaffen">O’Neill, Eugene</author>
               <date notBefore="1924-01-01" when="1924-07-01">1924</date>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/60603/</idno>
               <note type="work_kind">Drama &gt;&gt; Mehraktiges Drama</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pmb60605">
               <title>The Emperor Jones</title>
               <author ref="pmb5198" role="hat-geschaffen">O’Neill, Eugene</author>
               <date notBefore="1921-01-01" when="1921-07-02">1921</date>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/60605/</idno>
               <note type="work_kind">Drama &gt;&gt; Mehraktiges Drama</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pmb32917">
               <title>Schnitzler, Old, Admires America’s Young Vigor</title>
               <title type="werk_bibliografische-angabe">New York World, 1. 1. 1931</title>
               <author ref="pmb11277" role="hat-geschaffen">Ewen, David</author>
               <date when="1931-01-01">01.01.1931</date>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/32917/</idno>
               <note type="work_kind">Text</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pmb58357">
               <title>New York World</title>
               <title type="namensvariante">The World</title>
               <date from="1860-01-01" to="1931-07-02">1860 – 1931</date>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/58357/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1066835</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikipedia"
                  >https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_World</idno>
               <note type="work_kind">Periodikum &gt;&gt; Tageszeitung</note>
            </bibl>
         </listBibl>
         <listPlace>
            <place xml:id="pmb175">
               <placeName>Amerika</placeName>
               <desc type="entity_type">Kontinent (A.KNT)</desc>
               <desc type="entity_type_id">49</desc>
               <location type="coords">
                  <geo>32,530833 -117,02</geo>
               </location>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="geonames">https://sws.geonames.org/6255149/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-bahr"
                  >https://schnitzler-bahr.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb175.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/175/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-briefe"
                  >https://schnitzler-briefe.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pages/hits.html?searchkey=pmb175</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="kraus"
                  >https://kraus.wienbibliothek.at/register/orte/pmb175</idno>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="pmb254">
               <placeName>England</placeName>
               <desc type="entity_type">Land (A.LND)</desc>
               <desc type="entity_type_id">38</desc>
               <location type="coords">
                  <geo>52,483333 -1,566667</geo>
               </location>
               <location type="located_in_place">
                  <placeName ref="pmb34523">Vereinigtes Königreich</placeName>
                  <geo>54,75844 -2,69531</geo>
               </location>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-bahr"
                  >https://schnitzler-bahr.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb254.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/254/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-briefe"
                  >https://schnitzler-briefe.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pages/hits.html?searchkey=pmb254</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q21</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikipedia">https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/England</idno>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="pmb468">
               <placeName>Europa</placeName>
               <desc type="entity_type">Kontinent (A.KNT)</desc>
               <desc type="entity_type_id">49</desc>
               <location type="coords">
                  <geo>48,69096 9,14062</geo>
               </location>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q46</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="geonames">https://sws.geonames.org/6255148/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-bahr"
                  >https://schnitzler-bahr.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb468.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/468/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-briefe"
                  >https://schnitzler-briefe.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pages/hits.html?searchkey=pmb468</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="kraus"
                  >https://kraus.wienbibliothek.at/register/orte/pmb468</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                  >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb468.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikipedia">https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Europa</idno>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="pmb44053">
               <placeName>New York City</placeName>
               <placeName type="legacy-name-merge">New York</placeName>
               <placeName type="legacy-name-merge">New York, N. Y.</placeName>
               <placeName type="alternative-name">Neu-Amsterdam, NY</placeName>
               <placeName type="legacy-name-merge">New York, NY</placeName>
               <placeName type="alternative-name">Big Apple</placeName>
               <desc type="entity_type">https://www.geonames.org/ontology#P.PPL</desc>
               <desc type="entity_type_id">1412</desc>
               <location type="coords">
                  <geo>40,71427 -74,00597</geo>
               </location>
               <location type="located_in_place">
                  <placeName ref="pmb43406">Vereinigte Staaten von Amerika (USA)</placeName>
                  <geo>39,76 -98,5</geo>
               </location>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-bahr"
                  >https://schnitzler-bahr.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb5199.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/5199/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/44053/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="geonames">https://sws.geonames.org/5128581/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-briefe"
                  >https://schnitzler-briefe.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pages/hits.html?searchkey=pmb44053</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="kraus"
                  >https://kraus.wienbibliothek.at/register/orte/pmb44053</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                  >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb44053.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/98297/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="d-nb">https://d-nb.info/gnd/4042011-5</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q60</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikipedia"
                  >https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_City</idno>
            </place>
         </listPlace>
         <listOrg>
            <org xml:id="pmb29427">
               <orgName>Boston Symphony Orchestra</orgName>
               <desc type="entity_type">Orchester</desc>
               <desc type="entity_type_id">1011</desc>
               <location type="located_in_place">
                  <placeName ref="pmb889">Boston (Massachusetts)</placeName>
                  <geo>42,35843 -71,05977</geo>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-bahr"
                     >https://schnitzler-bahr.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb889.html</idno>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/889/</idno>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/6551/</idno>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/24805/</idno>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/47984/</idno>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="geonames">https://sws.geonames.org/4930956/</idno>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                     >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb889.html</idno>
               </location>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/29427/</idno>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="pmb29679">
               <orgName>Nobelpreis</orgName>
               <desc type="entity_type">Literaturpreis</desc>
               <desc type="entity_type_id">993</desc>
               <location type="located_in_place">
                  <placeName ref="pmb1119">Stockholm</placeName>
                  <geo>59,325 18,05</geo>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/1119/</idno>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/15661/</idno>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-briefe"
                     >https://schnitzler-briefe.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pages/hits.html?searchkey=pmb1119</idno>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/64053/</idno>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="geonames">https://sws.geonames.org/2673730/</idno>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                     >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb1119.html</idno>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/100625/</idno>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="d-nb">https://d-nb.info/gnd/4057648-6</idno>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1754</idno>
                  <idno type="URL" subtype="wikipedia"
                     >https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stockholm</idno>
               </location>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-bahr"
                  >https://schnitzler-bahr.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb29679.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/29679/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-briefe"
                  >https://schnitzler-briefe.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pages/hits.html?searchkey=pmb29679</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="kraus"
                  >https://kraus.wienbibliothek.at/register/institutionen/pmb29679</idno>
            </org>
         </listOrg>
      </back>
   </text></TEI>
