<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../meta/asischema.xsd"
   xml:base="schnitzler-interviews" xml:id="I032" next="I011" prev="I060" latex="\newpage">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">Arthur Schnitzler: »Das Zeitlose ist von kürzester Dauer.« Interviews,
               Meinungen, Proteste (1891–1931)</title>
            <title level="a" ref="#pmb33005">David Ewen: Anti-semitism, a Healthy Influence,
               26. 9. 1930</title>
            <title type="iso-date" when-iso="1930-09-26" n="1">26. 9. 1930</title>
            <author ref="#pmb11277">Ewen, David</author>
            <editor>
               <name>Müller, Martin Anton</name>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>ASI</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transkription und Kommentierung</resp>
               <name>Martin Anton Müller</name>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Martin Anton Müller</publisher>
            <idno type="asi" n="032"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listBibl>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#pmb11277">Ewen, David</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#pmb33005">Anti-semitism, a Healthy Influence</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j" ref="#pmb58355">The Canadian Jewish Chronicle</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1930-09-26" n="1">26. 9. 1930</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="jg">18</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">19</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">4, 17</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#pmb11277">Ewen, David</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#pmb33005">Anti-semitism, a Healthy Influence</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j">Jewish Exponent</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1930-09-26" n="1">26. 9. 1930</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="jg">87</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">1, 10</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#pmb11277">Ewen, David</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#pmb33005">How Anti-Semitism Helps the Jew</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j">The Literary Digest</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1930-10-18" n="1">18. 10. 1930</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="vol">107</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">2</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">26</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#pmb11277">Ewen, David</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#pmb33005">Wie der Antisemitismus den Juden hilft</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j">Die Auslese. Aus Zeitschriften des In- und Auslandes</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1930-11" n="1">November 1930</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="jg">4</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">11</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">682</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#pmb2121">Schnitzler, Arthur</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#pmb33005">Das Gute am Antisemitismus</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j" ref="#pmb61266">Neue Jüdische Monatsschau</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1931-09-01" n="1">1. 9. 1931</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="jg">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">9</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">8–9</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#pmb2121">Schnitzler, Arthur</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#pmb33005">Antisemitismus stärkt das Judentum. Ein
                        offenes Wort an die Christen</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j" ref="#pmb36376">Neues Wiener Journal</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1931-09-08" n="1">8. 9. 1931</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="jg">39</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">13.576</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">3</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="#pmb2121">Schnitzler, Arthur</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="#pmb33005">Perchè sono ebreo</title>
                     <editor>[Übersetzt von Guido Lodovico Luzzatto]</editor>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j">Israel</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1931-12-24" n="1">24. 12. 1931</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="jg">17</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">15</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">5</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <title level="a" ref="#pmb33001">Perchè sono ebreo</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Riedmann, Bettina</author>
                     <title level="m">Ich bin Jude, Österreicher, Deutscher. Judentum in Arthur
                        Schnitzlers Tagebüchern und Briefen</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="2002" n="1">2002</date>
                        <pubPlace>Tübingen</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Max Niemeyer</publisher>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">405–407</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
                  <series>
                     <title level="s">Conditio Judaica. Studien und Quellen zur deutsch-jüdischen
                        Literatur- und Kulturgeschichte</title>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">36</biblScope>
                  </series>
               </biblStruct>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en-US">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="approved">
         <change who="MAM" when="2017-11-17">angelegt</change>
         <change who="MAM" when="2018-02-14">Index check</change>
         <change who="KH" when="2021-10-29">Durchsicht</change>
      </revisionDesc>
      <!-- https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=re5OAAAAIBAJ&sjid=9ksDAAAAIBAJ&hl=de&pg=5841%2C1522175 -->
   </teiHeader><text type="text">
      <body>
         <div type="original" xml:lang="en-US">
            <head>
               <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="K_I032-1"/>Anti-semitism, a Healthy Influence<note
                  type="commentary" xml:id="K_I032-1h">Bei diesem Text handelt es sich um das am
                  häufigsten nachgedruckte Interview mit <rs type="person" ref="#pmb2121"
                     >Schnitzler</rs>, das ohne sein Wissen publiziert wurde und gegen dessen
                  spätere Gestalt er sich ein Jahr später verwahrt, <ref target="#P031"
                     type="pointer">.</ref>
               </note>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">By <rs type="person" ref="#pmb2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">As told to David Ewen</head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">
                  <rs type="person" ref="#pmb2121">Arthur Schnitzler</rs>, the world-famous Jewish
                  novelist and dramatist, presents some interesting views of the moot question of
                     <anchor type="textConst" xml:id="T_I032-2"/>anti-Semitism<c rendition="#dots"
                     n="3"/>
                  <note type="textConst" xml:id="T_I032-2h">
                     <quote>anti-Semitism<c rendition="#dots" n="2"/>
                     </quote>
                  </note> Himself touched by the <anchor type="textConst" xml:id="T_I032-1"/>hand
                     of<note type="textConst" xml:id="T_I032-1h">
                     <quote>hand</quote>
                  </note> bigotry, Schnitzler has some unique ideas on the problem and how best to
                  solve it. – Ed. Note.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <anchor type="label" xml:id="I032_L_society"/>
               <ref type="question" target="#q141"/>More than once during the course of my life have
               I come into contact with anti-Semitism. The first time I stumbled against it, I
               remember today very clearly; evidently it had made a very profound impression on me
               at the time. I was then a medical student at the <rs type="place" ref="#pmb386"
                  >University</rs>, here in <rs type="place" ref="#pmb50">Vienna</rs>, and a few of
               us were banded together into a sort of <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="KT118-1"
               />philanthropic society<note type="commentary" xml:id="KT118-1h">
                  <anchor type="label" xml:id="L_KT118-1"/>Diese Begebenheit erzählt <rs
                     type="person" ref="#pmb2121">Schnitzler</rs> ausführlicher in seiner
                  Autobiografie (<bibl>
                     <rs type="work" ref="#pmb33838">Jugend in Wien</rs> 157–158</bibl>).</note>
               whose mission was to give charity to needy students – not very much, just a few
               shillings to help them somewhat. Before the society was very many months <anchor
                  type="textConst" xml:id="TT118-1"/>old<note type="textConst" xml:id="TT118-1h">
                  <quote>oll</quote>
               </note>, discrimination set in. When a man was suggested for help, and his name was
               unmistakably Jewish, immediately he was subtly removed from every consideration. I
               was so struck by this unfair treatment that poor Jewish <anchor type="textConst"
                  xml:id="TT118-2"/>students<note type="textConst" xml:id="TT118-2h">
                  <quote>stuednts</quote>
               </note> received, that for a long while I fought bitterly against it. It was a
               hopeless fight, as I soon realized – and before long I was compelled to resign from
               the society. But after my graduation from the <rs type="place" ref="#pmb386"
                  >University</rs>, I was to learn that anti-Semitism was an everyday problem. As a
               physician I personally encountered so much of it that this, I am sure, more than
               anything else served to bring me sharply to Judaism and to an understanding of and a
               sympathy for its problems.</p>
            <p>
               <space dim="vertical" unit="line" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p>However, – although when I first encountered it, I was alarmed and infuriated at all
               anti-Semitism, however slight it might have been – I am not one of those who today
               look upon it as a very grave problem. Not that I deny the existence of anti-Semitism
               everywhere, but, frankly, I do not think it is a very important problem. As a matter
               of fact, I look upon anti-Semitism as a healthy influence in<pb/> the life of the
               Jew. Every once in a while a Jew will come to me, his face red with anger, his eyes
               flaming and desperate, and he will tell me how he has been the object of some
               anti-Semite’s obvious discrimination. I always try to calm such infuriated Jews and
               to tell them that they should not, after all, take such discrimination very
               seriously. It is just such discrimination – more than all the legends and religious
               worship – I tell them, which has kept Judaism palpitantly alive through the ages. And
               it is true. At least, I am convinced of it. Religion, that is strict religious
               beliefs according to age-old customs and traditions, has with each passing century
               become a weaker and weaker influence in the life of the ordinary Jew. We all see,
               each day, how little it plays a part in the everyday life of you and me, who,
               notwithstanding our disregard of the laws, still remain good Jews at heart. But
               though religious worship is becoming a weaker influence, racial patriotism persists
               tenaciously in the heart of every Jew, and as strongly as ever before. And the reason
               it does so, is because the average Jew well realizes that he is envied, abused, the
               object of the Christian world’s scorn and contempt. I do not, for example, believe
               that Jews were ever so radically patriotic as in these sordid years, of the past
               century, when they suffered the lash of persecution.</p>
            <p>Persecution, fortunately, has died out. Its legitimate offspring is anti-Semitism.
               And this anti-Semitism, I say, is serving a very useful purpose in constantly
               reminding the Jew that he is, after all, very individual; that he is, after all, very
               different from his Christian neighbour; that his only salvation in this world is to
               recognize this difference and to openly acknowledge it. Anti-Semitism, I feel, is
               constantly serving the healthy purpose of bringing into the heart of every Jew, far
               more forcefully than any other influence, I know of at the present moment, a
               patriotism for his race, and a love for his brother-Jews. That is why I say that
               anti-Semitism is a healthy influence.</p>
            <p>And then, why should we not reconcile ourselves gracefully to something that is so
               obviously inevitable as anti-Semitism is? Nothing that we can do can possibly
               overcome and put an end to anti-Semitism; it is simply out of the question.
               Anti-Semitism is a perfectly human failing of a perfectly human society. When a group
               of people is different from the vast majority, that group of people is certain to be
               scorned and held in contempt. And when that group, though in a minority, succeeds in
               forging to the front – in the world of art and industry and finance – envy is almost
               certain to light up the contempt of the majority into the mighty flame of hate.</p>
            <p>Realizing this, namely that anti-Semitism is inevitable in a human society, the Jew
               can do either of two things. He can either eliminate anti-Semitism by eliminating
               that which causes it. Or, in other words, he can surrender his race and its heritage.
               An absurd solution, to be sure! The other, and far more sensible, plan is simply to
               tolerate anti-Semitism as the fate that inevitably belongs to the Jew, a fate which
               cannot be changed. <rs type="person" ref="#pmb25217">Spinoza</rs> once wrote that an
               evil which is inevitable ceases to be an evil. For example, we die – certainly one of
               the most colossal tragedies in the life of the human-being (can anything be more evil
               than <anchor type="textConst" xml:id="T_I032-22"/>death?).<note type="textConst"
                  xml:id="T_I032-22h">
                  <quote>death?)</quote>
               </note> Yet, do we ever stop to worry over it? No. The fact that it is inevitable
               simply eliminates it as an evil; we accept it as a fact. Just so, should
               anti-Semitism be accepted. To fight against it is useless and merely serves to
               augment anti-Semitism, and not to diminish it. One cannot expect human-beings to be
               anything but human. Their shortcoming, however painful they may be sometimes, simply
               have to be understood – and tolerated.</p>
            <p>
               <space dim="vertical" unit="line" quantity="1"/>
            </p>
            <p>I am often asked if I believe that anti-Semitism will ever die. All things die in
               this world, and some day, in some way that I cannot for the moment foresee,
               anti-Semitism will go the way of all flesh. But that day is far, far off.
               Anti-Semitism is destined to linger as long as Jews remain Jews. For one thing, the
               causes of anti-Semitism can never be eliminated. Jews will always be different; Jews
               will always, I am sure, continue to be at the front of human activity; Jews must
               always be in a minority. Jews therefore will inevitably always be hated. And then,
               anti-Semitism is such a convenient thing! It is so convenient to discriminate, when
               discrimination is necessary. If, for example, a university is crowded, isn’t it
               convenient to put a ban against Jews? And in the case of our little philanthropic
               society, wasn’t discrimination against the Jew started because it was convenient –
               namely, more of the money could go to Christian students? Why, then, should society
               abandon anything so convenient? Especially since there is cause, from their point of
               view, for their discrimination? No. Some day perhaps a race of Supermen will appear
               in this world, in whom envy, hate, malice and contempt will be altogether foreign.
               But until such a time comes, the Jew is destined to suffer the stings and arrows of
               anti-Semitism.</p>
            <p>However, as I have already said, the Jews should not feel too deeply against –
               anti-Semitism. Strange to say, anti-Semitism is an evil which gives fruit to good.
               The Christians hope to annihilate us with their contempt; their contempt really makes
               us flourish. For never are we Jews more truly conscious of our race as when we
               realize that we are hated.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biographical">
            <div1>
               <ref type="schnitzler-tagebuch" target="1930-08-15"/>
               <quote>Nm. <rs type="person" ref="#pmb11277">David Ewes</rs>, junger Journalist <rs
                     type="place" ref="#pmb44053">New York</rs>, dem ich ein Interview abgeschlagen;
                  Gespräch.–</quote>
            </div1>
            <div1>
               <bibl>Schnitzler an <rs type="person" ref="#pmb20509">Sol Liptzin</rs>,
                     <date>10. 11. 1930</date>
               </bibl>
               <quote>Ich danke Ihnen sehr für Ihre liebe Karte, sowie für die eingesandten
                  Zeitungsausschnitte. Besonders der Artikel in dem jüdischen Blatt hat mich sehr
                  interessiert, denn lassen Sie mich gestehen, ich kann mich nicht erinnern, wann
                  ich ein Interview dieser Art gegeben hätte und weiß mich insbesondere des Autors,
                  ja auch nur seines Namens nicht zu erinnern. Der Fehler mag natürlich zum Teil bei
                  mir liegen. Ich sehe ja so viele Leute, daß mir nicht jeder Einzelne im Gedächtnis
                  bleibt. Eines weiß ich aber bestimmt, daß ich nie einem dieser Besucher das Recht
                  gegeben hatte ein Privatgespräch zum Zwecke einer Veröffentlichung zu verwenden.
                  Manches, was in dem Artikel steht, habe ich wohl gesagt, ich weiß nicht, ob zu
                  Herrn <rs type="person" ref="#pmb11277">Mahler</rs> oder zu jemandem andern; das
                  Meiste aber ist, ich will nicht geradezu sagen erfunden, aber doch so stilisiert,
                  daß meine eigene Ansicht und auch, wie ich glaube, mein Wesen keineswegs so
                  herauskommt, wie es der Wirklichkeit entspricht. Übrigens ist der Artikel rein
                  journalistisch genommen gar nicht so übel und gewiß von den besten Absichten
                  diktiert. Ich bitte Sie auch diesen Brief als rein privat zu betrachten, denn ich
                  wünsche keineswegs <rs type="person" ref="#pmb11277">Gilbert Mahler</rs> oder wie
                  er sonst heißen möge, Unannehmlichkeiten zu bereiten.</quote>
            </div1>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listPerson>
            <person xml:id="pmb11277">
               <persName>
                  <forename>David</forename>
                  <surname>Ewen</surname>
               </persName>
               <birth>
                  <date when="1907-11-26">26.11.1907</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb46224">
                     <placeName type="pref">Lviv</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>49,83826 24,02324</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </birth>
               <death>
                  <date when="1985-12-28">28.12.1985</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb45749">
                     <placeName type="pref">Miami</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>25,77427 -80,19366</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </death>
               <sex value="male"/>
               <occupation ref="pmb99">Journalist/Journalistin</occupation>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                  >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/person_14828</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="d-nb">https://d-nb.info/gnd/1089844891</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/11277/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q9202613</idno>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pmb2121">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Arthur</forename>
                  <surname>Schnitzler</surname>
               </persName>
               <birth>
                  <date when="1862-05-15">15.05.1862</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb50">
                     <placeName type="pref">Wien</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>48,2066 16,37341</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </birth>
               <death>
                  <date when="1931-10-21">21.10.1931</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb50">
                     <placeName type="pref">Wien</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>48,2066 16,37341</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </death>
               <sex value="male"/>
               <occupation ref="pmb90">Schriftsteller/Schriftstellerin</occupation>
               <occupation ref="pmb97">Mediziner/Medizinerin</occupation>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="d-nb">https://d-nb.info/gnd/118609807</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-bahr"
                  >https://schnitzler-bahr.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb2121.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/2121/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-briefe"
                  >https://schnitzler-briefe.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pages/hits.html?searchkey=pmb2121</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                  >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/pmb2121</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="fackel">https://fackel.oeaw.ac.at/?p=fackelp38500</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="kraus1933"
                  >https://kraus1933.ace.oeaw.ac.at/Gesamt.xml?template=register_personen.html&amp;letter=S#DWpers0212</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="doi">https://doi.org/10.1553/0x00284416</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q44331</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikipedia"
                  >https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Schnitzler</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-kino"
                  >https://schnitzler-kino.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb2121.html</idno>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pmb25217">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Baruch de</forename>
                  <surname>Spinoza</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="person_namensvariante_vorname">Benedictus</persName>
               <birth>
                  <date when="1632-11-24">24.11.1632</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb40709">
                     <placeName type="pref">Amsterdam</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>52,37403 4,88969</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </birth>
               <death>
                  <date when="1677-02-21">21.02.1677</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb58810">
                     <placeName type="pref">Den Haag</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>52,07667 4,29861</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </death>
               <sex value="male"/>
               <occupation ref="pmb154">Philosoph/Philosophin</occupation>
               <occupation ref="pmb3065">Augenoptiker/Augenoptikerin</occupation>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                  >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/person_20265</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/25217/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="kraus"
                  >https://kraus.wienbibliothek.at/register/personen/pmb25217</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="fackel">https://fackel.oeaw.ac.at/?p=fackelp53496</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/116117/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="d-nb">https://d-nb.info/gnd/118616242</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q35802</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikipedia"
                  >https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baruch_de_Spinoza</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="thun-korrespondenz"
                  >https://thun-korrespondenz.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/spinoza-baruch.html</idno>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pmb20509">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Sol</forename>
                  <surname>Liptzin</surname>
               </persName>
               <birth>
                  <date when="1901-07-27">27.07.1901</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb60607">
                     <placeName type="pref">Sataniv</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>49,25481 26,25417</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </birth>
               <death>
                  <date when="1995-11-15">15.11.1995</date>
                  <settlement ref="pmb5297">
                     <placeName type="pref">Jerusalem</placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo>31,76904 35,21633</geo>
                     </location>
                  </settlement>
               </death>
               <sex value="male"/>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                  >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/person_17586</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-bahr"
                  >https://schnitzler-bahr.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb20509.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/20509/</idno>
            </person>
         </listPerson>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pmb33838">
               <title>Jugend in Wien</title>
               <title type="namensvariante">Leben und Nachklang, Werk und Widerhall</title>
               <title type="werk_link"
                  >http://www.zeno.org/Literatur/M/Schnitzler,+Arthur/Autobiographisches/Jugend+in+Wien</title>
               <author ref="pmb2121" role="hat-geschaffen">Schnitzler, Arthur</author>
               <date notBefore="1968-01-01" when="1968-07-01">1968</date>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="asaf">https://asaf.com/S.04.03.04</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q41815908</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-bahr"
                  >https://schnitzler-bahr.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb31377.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/31377/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/33838/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-briefe"
                  >https://schnitzler-briefe.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pages/hits.html?searchkey=pmb33838</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                  >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb33838.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikipedia"
                  >https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jugend_in_Wien</idno>
               <note type="work_kind">Biografie &gt;&gt; Autobiografie</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pmb33005">
               <title>Anti-semitism, a Healthy Influence</title>
               <title type="werk_bibliografische-angabe">The Canadian Jewish Chronicle, 26. 9.
                  1930</title>
               <author ref="pmb11277" role="hat-geschaffen">Ewen, David</author>
               <date when="1930-09-26">26.09.1930</date>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/33005/</idno>
               <note type="work_kind">Text</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pmb58355">
               <title>The Canadian Jewish Chronicle</title>
               <date>None</date>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/58355/</idno>
               <note type="work_kind">Periodikum &gt;&gt; Zeitschrift &gt;&gt; Wochenschrift</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pmb61266">
               <title>Neue jüdische Monatsschau</title>
               <date>None</date>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/61266/</idno>
               <note type="work_kind">Periodikum &gt;&gt; Zeitschrift &gt;&gt; Monatsschrift</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pmb36376">
               <title>Neues Wiener Journal</title>
               <title type="werk_link-anno">http://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=nwj</title>
               <author ref="pmb36371" role="hat-einen-beitrag-geschaffen-zu">Papp,
                  Desiderius</author>
               <author ref="pmb10815" role="hat-einen-beitrag-geschaffen-zu">Bahr, Hermann</author>
               <date to="1939-01-01">1893 – 1939</date>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/36376/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-briefe"
                  >https://schnitzler-briefe.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pages/hits.html?searchkey=pmb36376</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="kraus"
                  >https://kraus.wienbibliothek.at/register/werke/pmb36376</idno>
               <note type="work_kind">Periodikum &gt;&gt; Tageszeitung</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pmb33001">
               <title>Artur Schnitzler läßt sich nicht interviewen!</title>
               <title type="werk_bibliografische-angabe">Neues Wiener Journal, 18. 9. 1931</title>
               <author ref="pmb2121" role="hat-geschaffen">Schnitzler, Arthur</author>
               <date when="1931-09-18">18.09.1931</date>
               <idno type="URL" subtype=""
                  >http://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=nwj&amp;datum=19310918&amp;seite=1&amp;zoom=33</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/33001/</idno>
               <note type="work_kind">Text</note>
            </bibl>
         </listBibl>
         <listPlace>
            <place xml:id="pmb386">
               <placeName>Universität Wien</placeName>
               <desc type="entity_type">Universität (K.UNI)</desc>
               <desc type="entity_type_id">15</desc>
               <location type="coords">
                  <geo>48,213018714231 16,36086067999</geo>
               </location>
               <location type="located_in_place">
                  <placeName ref="pmb51">I., Innere Stadt</placeName>
                  <geo>48,20769 16,37049</geo>
               </location>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-bahr"
                  >https://schnitzler-bahr.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb386.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/386/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-briefe"
                  >https://schnitzler-briefe.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pages/hits.html?searchkey=pmb386</idno>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="pmb50">
               <placeName>Wien</placeName>
               <placeName type="ort_fruherer_name">K.K. Reichshaupt- und Residenzstadt
                  Wien</placeName>
               <placeName type="alternative-name">Bécs</placeName>
               <placeName type="alternative-name">Land Wien</placeName>
               <placeName type="alternative-name">Vídeň</placeName>
               <placeName type="alternative-name">Wenia</placeName>
               <placeName type="alternative-name">Beč</placeName>
               <placeName type="ort_fruherer_name">Vindobona</placeName>
               <placeName type="alternative-name">Vienna</placeName>
               <placeName type="x_zum-loschen-markiert">Wien?</placeName>
               <desc type="entity_type">Besiedelter Ort (A.BSO)</desc>
               <desc type="entity_type_id">14</desc>
               <location type="coords">
                  <geo>48,2066 16,37341</geo>
               </location>
               <location type="located_in_place">
                  <placeName ref="pmb41240">Österreich</placeName>
                  <geo>47,33333 13,33333</geo>
               </location>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="geonames">https://sws.geonames.org/2761369/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="d-nb">https://d-nb.info/gnd/4066009-6</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-bahr"
                  >https://schnitzler-bahr.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb50.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/50/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/2316/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/20954/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-briefe"
                  >https://schnitzler-briefe.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pages/hits.html?searchkey=pmb50</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/65221/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/65223/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="kraus"
                  >https://kraus.wienbibliothek.at/register/orte/pmb50</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                  >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb50.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1741</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikipedia">https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wien</idno>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="pmb44053">
               <placeName>New York City</placeName>
               <placeName type="legacy-name-merge">New York</placeName>
               <placeName type="legacy-name-merge">New York, N. Y.</placeName>
               <placeName type="alternative-name">Neu-Amsterdam, NY</placeName>
               <placeName type="legacy-name-merge">New York, NY</placeName>
               <placeName type="alternative-name">Big Apple</placeName>
               <desc type="entity_type">https://www.geonames.org/ontology#P.PPL</desc>
               <desc type="entity_type_id">1412</desc>
               <location type="coords">
                  <geo>40,71427 -74,00597</geo>
               </location>
               <location type="located_in_place">
                  <placeName ref="pmb43406">Vereinigte Staaten von Amerika (USA)</placeName>
                  <geo>39,76 -98,5</geo>
               </location>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-bahr"
                  >https://schnitzler-bahr.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb5199.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/5199/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/44053/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="geonames">https://sws.geonames.org/5128581/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-briefe"
                  >https://schnitzler-briefe.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pages/hits.html?searchkey=pmb44053</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="kraus"
                  >https://kraus.wienbibliothek.at/register/orte/pmb44053</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="schnitzler-tagebuch"
                  >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/pmb44053.html</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="pmb">https://pmb.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/entity/98297/</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="d-nb">https://d-nb.info/gnd/4042011-5</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikidata">http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q60</idno>
               <idno type="URL" subtype="wikipedia"
                  >https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_City</idno>
            </place>
         </listPlace>
      </back>
   </text></TEI>
